all at their friends and now we're going to talk about collections it's a
comprehensive API again provides you lots of interfaces and lots of lots of
classes which implement those interfaces and we'll just have a look at why do we
use collections and then how do we use them so again as the philosophy goes first
the why and then the how and the why is why are we talking about collections
today so I'll just write some pointers for you that will make it clear why are
we even doing this video so you remember we use arrays all the time but there
are significant disadvantages of arrays and the disadvantages that what you
have to put the size before compile time and once you put the size it cannot
be changed what that means is it's not a growable data structure it's not a
shrinkable data structure right those are glaring disadvantages working with
arrays and a good analogy to understand that would be let's say you are
working for a you're developing a school management system you're providing them
with a solution and they expect that in this session 500 students would new
students would join in but let's say it's the times of COVID and only 100 join
in what happens to that 400 blocks of memory that you had reserved if you're
working with arrays that goes waste there is no way you can delete that and let's
say in another world instead of 500 they get 800 new admissions so they
cannot change we cannot add more memory bytes at runtime another disadvantage
that's why I say arrays is there are not a growable data structure neither
they are shrinkable and that's where collections come into the picture they
provide you all of that and much more right so first things first about
collections is that collections can store objects in Java don't matter what
those objects are obviously rubber class objects strings custom class
objects we can store all of them but never permit use right and for storing
primitives we have a workaround I'll just brief you on that later on so they
can store objects they are growable they are shrinkable as well right so
that means that whatever and it's very important for you to understand that
there are a lot of collection classes out there right but all of them share
these same properties and traits and they would have something of their own
that is unique to those particular collection classes but these properties are
common to all of them they're growable they are shrinkable they are short
table as well and they are searchables right so all of these
properties are common to all collection classes as I said they bring this
much to the table and much much more and when once we write the code once we
talk about a particular collection classes you will know why I say they bring
so much to the table so it's very important to understand that all of them
share the same properties but they have uniqueness to them as well right and
then another property I want you to understand about collections whenever
you're dealing with collections is that that is ordering and sorting so this
place a role for you to decide which collection class to use in what
situation right now what is ordering ordering is how are the values stored in a
data structure if you put them for example and let's take an example with
areas let's say you enter user enters at runtime these values let's say 31 65
93 2 and 7 60 and then once you print them once user let's say a for loop or
enhanced for loop Java 5 enhanced for loop to traverse them what is the output
that you get in the order they would be saved right what is the order that
that would be saved right so obviously you will get 31 65 93 2 and 7 60 that
means in the order that that you inserted is the order in which they were
stored it is always do that right but we shouldn't take that for granted until
now we have why because areas always maintain what we say is the insertion order
we call it the insertion order what does that mean in the order in which you
insert the elements is the order in which they actually would be stored that's
called insertion order but is this sorted as well no not really it isn't sorted
so we say areas always are ordered but not sorted right so some of the
certain some of the Kalisha classes out there which you will come across
shortly they would be acting like arrays in terms of ordering and sorting they
would be just insert they'll be following the insertion order but not sorted but
some of the other Kalisha classes they would be different how let's say there's
a Kalisha class where you insert values like this and then they end up big
stored like this and when you bring them you get there this like this you get
two 31 65 93 and 7 60 right there's something look interesting here yes
they're sorted right that means you insert it like this but they're actually
stored in sorted order and those Kalisha classes we say they're ordered as
well as sorted sorted in natural ordering see it's ascending order we call that
as natural ordering all right and then there would be a third situation where
you inserted like this but actually you get them stored like this
right so is there some order to this is there any sorting order to this not
at all that means they are unordered and sorted and there are a few
collection glasses that that allow you to do that right that is which do not
maintain any order and if they are not ordered they are not sorted right the
fourth situation this is my question to you right is that can there be a
collection class which allows you to enter data and then give you
unordered but sorted collection can there be a situation where they provide you
unordered but sorted no there can't be why because sorting in itself is an
order it would be like I'll tell you to sort your books at home today so you'll
come back to me you'll say in what order will eat I'll say no just sort them
right that doesn't make any sense you'll say no I need to know which order by
author me by reverse author name by price by reverse price high to low and low
to high or by the publication date there has to be an order that's why I say
sorting in itself is an order so the fourth situation cannot cannot occur
right so three situation can occur and that's about ordering and sorting
will see which glasses provide us what